<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <content>
    <headers headerID="p1x101.0y712.0">
      <title>Time-Varying Channel Tracking for Space-Time Block Coding</title>
      <authors>
        <author>
          <author-first>M.</author-first>
          <author-last>Enescu</author-last>
        </author>
        and
        <author>
          <author-first>V.</author-first>
          <author-last>Koivunen</author-last>
        </author>
      </authors>
      <institution>Signal Processing Laboratory Helsinki University of Technology</institution>
      <address>P.O. Box 3000, FIN-02015 HUT, Finland</address>
      <abstract>Abstract --- This paper addresses the problem of channel estimation and tracking for space-time block coding. Channel tracking performance is investigated using several recursive algorithms. In the simulations it is shown that different channel tracking procedures can be used in several scenarios. As a performance criterion the orthogonality property of the decoding matrix is considered. A realistic channel model developed in COST 207 project is used in our examples.</abstract>
    </headers>
    <body>I. INTRODUCTION 
Time-varying multipath fading is a fundamental phenomenon which 
makes the wireless transmission difficult. In most scattering 
environments, antenna diversity is a practical technique for reducing the 
effect of multipath fading [8]. Space-Time block coding (STBC) is a 
simple transmit diversity technique which improves the signal quality 
at the receiver by simple processing using two antennas at the 
transmitter. This type of coding/decoding scheme introduced by Alamouti 
[1], is based on channel estimates at the receiver in order to decode 
the transmitted symbols. 
The problem of channel tracking for STBC was also investigated 
in [9]. This paper is motivated by investigating the performance of 
several solutions for channel estimation and tracking. A class of 
recursive algorithms (LMS, RLS, Kalman) and ST decoding are used to 
acquire the channel and decode the information symbols with 
diversity gains. A detailed description of how to link the symbol decoding 
stage with channel tracking stage is also presented. Extensive 
simulations show the performance of the tracking algorithms in scenarios 
where time-varying channels were generated based on the channel 
model derived in COST 207 project [3]. 
The rest of the paper is organized as follows. In the next section 
we present the system model and the coding/decoding technique. In 
section three we give a description of the recursive algorithms used 
for channel tracking and we present how to link the symbol 
decoding stage with the channel estimation stage. Simulation results are 
presented in section four. We conclude this paper with a discussion. 
II. SYSTEM MODEL 
A Coding 
The coding scheme suggested by Alamouti works in the following 
manner. The original symbol stream is divided in two separate 
symbol streams which are then transmitted using two antennas such that 
we receive the following signal y: 
y2k = s2k h1;2k + s 2k+1h2;2k + w 2k (1) 
y 2k+1 = s # 
2k+1 h 1;2k+1 + s # 
2k h2;2k+1 + w2k+1 (2) 
ENCODER 
ST 
-s(2k+1) * 
s(2k) * 
h 2 
h 1 
s(2k+1) 
s(2k) 
s(2k) 
s(2k+1) 
y(k) 
w(k) 
Figure 1: ST transmission diagram 
where h 1;2k and h 2;2k denote the channel taps h1 and h2 at moment 
2k, s is the transmitted symbol, w is additive white Gaussian noise 
(AWGN) and # denotes complex conjugate. The transmission model 
using STBC is presented in Figure 1. After applying complex 
conjugation on the signal received at time index 2k +1we have the 
following vector model: 
y = Hs +w (3) 
where the vector y = 
# y2k y # 
2k+1 # T 
contains the received signal, 
the vector s =[s 2k s2k+1 ] T represents the transmitted information, 
w = 
# w 2k w # 
2k+1 
# T represents the additive Gaussian noise and the 
channel matrix H can be written in the following form: 
H = # h1;2k h2;2k 
h # 
2;2k+1 h # 
1;2k+1 
# (4) 
B Decoding 
Based on the model (3) we start by forming the matrix H as shown 
in (4). In order to estimate the transmitted symbols s we compute the 
soft estimate z =[z 2k z2k+1 ] T as follows: 
# z2k 
z 2k+1 
# = H H # y2k 
y # 
2k+1 
# : (5) 
The independent estimation of the transmitted symbols ^ s 2k and ^ s 2k+1 
is possible due to the fact that the outputs z 2k and z 2k+1 are decou- 
pled. This is due to the orthogonality property of the matrix H, hence 
H H H is diagonal. The symbols [^s 2k ^ s2k+1 ] T are estimated from the 
vector [z 2k z2k+1 ] T using a decision device, actually this is the ML 
receiver in the case of flat fading channels. The orthogonality 
condition of H is the key property that must be preserved both at the 
transmitter and receiver in order to achieve error free decoding. To 
attain this goal, good estimates of the channel must be available at 
the receiver. From now on the estimated channel taps at time index k 
will be written in vector form: ^ 
h (kjk) = 
# ^ h 1;(kjk) 
^ h 2;(kjk) # T 
. The 
decoding technique can be summarized as follows: 
1. Predict ^ h (2kj2k 2) 
^ 
h (2k+1j2k 1) : 
2. Form the matrix H as described in (4). 
3. Decode ^ s 2k and ^ s 2k+1 as shown in (5). 
The prediction of the channels may not be accurate. In this 
case one can use the previous filtered estimates ^ h (2kj2k 2) = 
^ 
h (2k 2j2k 2) and ^ h (2k+1j2k 1) = ^ h (2k 1j2k 1) ). In time-varying 
scenarios the candidates for channel tracking are recursive algorithms 
such as LMS, RLS, Kalman. 
III. CHANNEL TRACKING 
We start this section by pointing out that at each even and odd time 
indices we have to form the decoded information vector as follows: 
at time 2k we have ^ s even = [^s 2k ^ s2k+1 ] T and at time 2k +1we 
use ^ s odd =[ ^ s # 
2k+1 ^ s # 
2k ] T . As mentioned before, the prediction of 
the channel taps may not be possible. In such case we can use the 
previous estimated values, i.e. ^ h 1;(2kj2k 2) = ^ h 1;(2k 2j2k 2) and 
^ h 1;(2k+1j2k 1) = ^ h 1;(2k 1j2k 1) . In the rest of the section we will 
briefly present the update rules of LMS, RLS and Kalman [6]. 
A LMS 
Least Mean Squares algorithm has low complexity but does not 
have good tracking capabilities and convergence slowly. However, it 
can be used to track slow time-varying channels. The algorithm may 
be summarized as follows: 
for each k do: 
use the estimated information vector ^ s even or ^ s odd 
according to the time index. 
ek = yk ^ s T 
k 
^ h (kjk 1) 
^ 
h (kjk) = ^ 
h kjk 1 + #ek^ sk 
where # is the adaptation step. 
B RLS 
RLS has satisfactory tracking capabilities and higher complexity. 
The algorithm may be summarized as follows: 
for each k do: 
use the estimated information vector ^ s even or ^ s odd 
according to time index. 
ek = yk ^ s T 
k 
^ h (kjk 1) 
kk = P^ s T 
k (# + ^ s T 
k P^ sk ) 1 
P =(P kk^ s T 
k P )=# 
^ 
h (kjk) = ^ 
h (kjk 1) + ekP^ sk 
where # is the forgetting factor. 
C Kalman 
The algorithm may be summarized as follows: 
for each k do: 
use the estimated information vector ^ s even or ^ s odd 
according to time index. 
^ 
h (kjk 1) = A ^ h (k 1jk 1) 
P (kjk 1) = AP (k 1jk 1) A T +Q 
kk = P (kjk 1) ^ sk (# 2 
w + ^ s T 
k P (kjk 1) ^ sk ) 1 
h (kjk) = ^ 
h (kjk 1) + kk 
# yk ^ s T 
k 
^ h (kjk 1) 
# 
P (kjk) = P (kjk 1) kk^ s T 
k P (kjk 1) 
The practical implementation of the algorithm consists of putting 
together the symbol detection stage with one of the tracking 
algorithms presented earlier. The algorithms proceed as follows: 
# Wait until two consecutive values of y 2k and y 2k+1 become 
available. 
# Decode the information vector s as described in the decoding 
section. 
# Use the decoded symbols to estimate the channel ^ 
h (2kj2k) and 
^ 
h (2k+1j2k+1) using one of the algorithms presented in sections 
(A)-(C). 
IV. SIMULATIONS 
In this section simulation results are performed according to ETSI 
[11] recommendations. Regarding the channels types to be used, the 
following scenarios are suggested: 1st scenario Indoor/Low range 
outdoor where a Typical Urban (TU) can be used with a receiver 
speed of 3 km/h, up to 10 km/h. 2nd scenario is about urban 
environment characterized by TU at 50 km/h up to 150 km/h and suburban 
outdoor where we use Hilly Terrain (HT) at 100 km/h. The 3rd 
scenario defines the Rural outdoor characterized by the Rural Area (RA) 
type of channel with the receiver speed in the range 130-250 km/h 
and HT at 100 km/h. 
The channel impulse response used in simulations is a time- 
selective fading channel, i.e. time-varying but frequency flat. It 
is obtained as a superposition of Np = 100 paths and can 
be described using the Gaussian distributed Wide-Sense 
Stationary with Uncorrelated Scattering (WSSUS) model [7]: h i (t) = 
1= 
p Np 
P Np 
p=1 
e j(2#f d;p t+#p ) 
hRF (t), where f d;p is the Doppler 
spread, #p is the angular spread and hRF (t) is the impulse response of 
the receive filter. This model is suitable for many channels of 
practical interest in mobile wireless communications [3]. For a more 
extensive presentation of COST 207 we refer the reader to [10]. Linearized 
GMSK modulation was used in our simulations [2]. 
Alamouti's coding/decoding scheme is based on the 
orthogonality of the channel matrix H, i.e. H H H should be diagonal. At each 
time step 2k we compute the product P = H H H. The off-diagonal 
complex terms of P are squared and added. Let us call the absolute 
value of this sum the performance index. In the ideal case of perfect 
channel estimation the performance index must be zero for any time 
index 2k. The most important goal of channel tracking is to preserve 
the orthogonality property of H. However, complexity is an 
important issue of future algorithms. In some scenarios suggested by ETSI 
some other adaptive algorithms, such as RLS, may give satisfactory 
performance. 
In the first experiment we want to illustrate the channel tracking 
capability. Figures (2) and (3) show the true channels (solid lines) 
and their corresponding estimated values (dash lines) in the case of 
HT for a receiver speed of 100 km/h. Only one of the two channels 
is shown. Re-training sequences of 15 symbols were used after each 
200 transmitted symbols in order to avoid divergence. The length 
of the initial training sequence was of 20 symbols. We observe that 
RLS gives good tracking results, LMS can find the channel but is 
loosing the track. Kalman exhibits good tracking capability despite 
the fact that it temporarily loosing the track of the imaginary part of 
the channel. 
In figure (4) a comparison of LMS, RLS, Kalman and Kalman 
smoothing is performed varying the SNR. For a detailed 
implementation of Kalman smoothing to STBC channel tracking see [5]. Rural 
Area type of channels with a receiver speed of 70 km/h were used and 
the results were averaged over 100 realizations. This example fits in 
the second scenario suggested by ETSI. We observe that Kalman and 
Kalman smoothing give good results, however, RLS has similar 
performance and can successfully be used. On the contrary, LMS fails 
due to the time variations of the channel. 
0 200 400 600 800 1000 1200 1400 1600 1800 2000 
0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
Re(h 
1 
) 
0 200 400 600 800 1000 1200 1400 1600 1800 2000 
0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
Re(h 
1 
) 
0 200 400 600 800 1000 1200 1400 1600 1800 2000 
0 
0.5 
1 
Re(h 
1 
) 
number of samples 
LMS 
RLS 
Kalman 
Figure 2: Hilly Terrain, 100 km/h, 20dB, solid line is real part 
of the true channel, dash line is real part of the estimated 
channel using LMS, RLS and Kalman. 
In the next example we want to emphasize the benefits of using the 
smoothing technique in a demanding scenario 1 . RA-type of channel 
with a receiver speed of 200 km/h is used at SNR 8 dB. This 
simulation is in the third category suggested by ETSI. Four algorithms 
are compared in channel estimation and tracking: regular Kalman, 
Kalman smoothing, RLS and LMS. The performance index is 
calculated for every simulation and averaged over 100 realizations. The 
boxplot of the averaged performance indices is depicted in Figure 5. 
The box has lines at the lower quartile, median, and upper quartile 
values. The lines extending from each end show the extent of the rest 
of the results with outliers presented as crosses. It can be observed 
that the smoothing technique has the most stable performance. As 
can be shown from figure (5 simulations have been performed also 
with LMS, however, it has a poor performance. A zoom of the 
boxplot figure was made in order to put more emphasis on the first three 
1 By demanding scenario we understand a receiver with high speed in a 
difficult environment at low SNR. 
0 200 400 600 800 1000 1200 1400 1600 1800 2000 
-4 
-2 
0 
2 
4 
Im(h 
1 
) 
0 200 400 600 800 1000 1200 1400 1600 1800 2000 
-4 
-2 
0 
2 
4 
Im(h 
1 
) 
0 200 400 600 800 1000 1200 1400 1600 1800 2000 
-4 
-2 
0 
2 
4 
Im(h 
1 
) 
number of samples 
LMS 
RLS 
Kalman 
Figure 3: Hilly Terrain, 100 km/h, 20dB, solid line is 
imaginary part of the true channel, dash line is imaginary part of the 
estimated channel using LMS, RLS and Kalman. 
0 5 10 15 20 25 
10 -3 
10 -2 
10 -1 
10 0 
 
known channel 
RLS tracking 
Kalman tracking 
Kalman smoothing 
LMS tracking 
Figure 4: Comparison of LMS, RLS, Kalman and Kalman 
smoothing tracking, RA - 70 km/h. 
algorithms. 
In the next simulation we focus on the second ETSI scenario. 
We use regular Kalman, smoothing Kalman and RLS and LMS. The 
channel type is HT with a receiver speed of 100 km/h and SNR 8 
dB. The performance index is shown in Figure 6. We observe that 
RLS has a satisfactory performance. Thus, it could be used in not 
so demanding scenarios. As in the previous case LMS fails. Finally, 
in the most easy scenario proposed by ETSI, a TU channel is used 
with a receiver speed of 30 km/h and SNR 5 dB. The tracking 
algorithms are regular Kalman, smoothing Kalman, LMS and RLS. The 
performance index is shown in Figure 7. 
V. DISCUSSION 
In this paper several recursive algorithms have been applied for STBC 
channel tracking. It has been shown by simulations that in not so 
demanding scenarios, good tracking performance can be achieved using 
1 2 3 4 
0 
0.01 
0.02 
0.03 
0.04 
0.05 
0.06 
0.07 
0.08 
0.09 
0.1 
performance 
index 
algorithm number 
RA - 200 km/h, 8dB SNR 
Figure 5: Performance index based on the orthogonality of H. 
Algorithm numbers correspond (in order): Kalman, Kalman 
smoothing, RLS, LMS. 
1 2 3 4 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
x 10 -4 
performance 
index 
algorithm number 
HT - 100 km/h, 8 dB SNR 
Figure 6: Performance index based on the orthogonality of H. 
Algorithm numbers correspond (in order): Kalman, Kalman 
smoothing, RLS, LMS. 
LMS with relatively low computations. When one antenna is used at 
the receiver complexity is not high even when using Kalman filter 
since the operation that generates high complexity (computing the 
inverse in the Kalman gain) is a scalar division. The complexity is 
an issue when more than one antenna is used at the receiver. Then 
we have to invert a matrix having the dimension proportional to the 
number of receive antennas and complexity is increasing. Another 
problem when using Kalman is that one needs to know noise 
statistics needed (i.e. the measurement and noise covariances). In this 
paper they have been assumed to be known, however, in real 
situations they have to be estimated from the data [4] if one expects near 
optimal performance.</body>
    <biblio>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y492.0">
        <ref-marker>[1]</ref-marker>
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Alamouti,</author-last>
            <author-first>S.</author-first>
            <author-middle>M.,</author-middle>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>"A simple transmit diversity technique for wireless communications",</title>
        <journal>IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications,</journal>
        <volume>vol. 16,</volume>
        <number>no. 8,</number>
        <pages>pp. 1451-1458,</pages>
        <date>1998.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y460.0">
        <ref-marker>[2]</ref-marker>
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-first>Z.</author-first>
            <author-last>Ding,</author-last>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>G.</author-first>
            <author-last>Li,</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>"Single-Channel Blind Equalization for GSM Cellular Systems",</title>
        <journal>IEEE J. Select. Areas. Commun.,</journal>
        <volume>Vol. 16,</volume>
        <pages>1493 - 1505,</pages>
        <date>Oct. 1998.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y427.0">
        <ref-marker>[3]</ref-marker>
        <reference-hlabeled>"</reference-hlabeled>
        <title>Digital Land Mobile Radio Communications - COST 207",</title>
        <institution>Commission of the European Communities, Office for Official Publications of the European Communities,</institution>
        <address>Luxembourg,</address>
        <date>Mar. 14, 1984 - Sept. 13, 1988</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y395.0">
        <ref-marker>[4]</ref-marker>
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-first>M.</author-first>
            <author-last>Enescu,</author-last>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>M.</author-first>
            <author-last>Sirbu,</author-last>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>V.</author-first>
            <author-last>Koivunen,</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>"Adaptive Equalization of MIMO time-varying channels",</title>
        <institution>submitted to Signal Processing,</institution>
        <date>May 2001.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y372.0">
        <ref-marker>[5]</ref-marker>
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-first>M.</author-first>
            <author-last>Enescu,</author-last>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>V.</author-first>
            <author-last>Koivunen,</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>"Kalman smoothing based channel estimation for space-time block coding",</title>
        <conference>submitted to EUSIPCO</conference>
        <date>2002,</date>
        <address>Toulouse, France.</address>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y340.0">
        <ref-marker>[6]</ref-marker>
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-first>S.</author-first>
            <author-last>Haykin,</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>"Adaptive Filter Theory", 3rd edition,</title>
        <publisher>Prentice-Hall,</publisher>
        <date>1996.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y326.0">
        <ref-marker>[7]</ref-marker>
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-first>P.</author-first>
            <author-last>Hoeher,</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>"A Statistical Discrete-Time Model for the WSSUS Multipath Channel",</title>
        <journal>IEEE Trans. on Vehicular Technology,</journal>
        <volume>vol. 41,</volume>
        <number>no. 4,</number>
        <date>1992,</date>
        <pages>461-468.</pages>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y294.0">
        <ref-marker>[8]</ref-marker>
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-first>W.</author-first>
            <author-middle>C.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Jakes,</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>Ed. "Microwave Mobile Communications",</title>
        <address>New York:</address>
        <publisher>Wiley,</publisher>
        <date>1974.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y271.0">
        <ref-marker>[9]</ref-marker>
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-first>Z.</author-first>
            <author-last>Liu,</author-last>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>X.</author-first>
            <author-last>Ma</author-last>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>G.</author-first>
            <author-middle>B.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Giannakis,</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>" Space-Time Coding and Kalman Filtering for Diversity Transmissions through Time-Selective Fading Channels",</title>
        <conference>Proc. of MILCOM Conf.,</conference>
        <address>Los Angeles, CA,</address>
        <date>Oct.</date>
        <pages>pp. 22-25,</pages>
        <date>2000.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y238.0">
        <ref-marker>[10]</ref-marker>
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Molisch,</author-last>
            <author-first>A.</author-first>
            <author-middle>F.,</author-middle>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>"Wideband wireless digital communications",</title>
        <publisher>Prentice Hall,</publisher>
        <date>2000.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p4x303.0y215.0">
        <ref-marker>[11]</ref-marker>
        <author>ETSI Normalization Committee,</author>
        <reference-hlabeled>"</reference-hlabeled>
        <title>Digital cellular telecommunications system (Phase 2+); Enhanced Data rates for GSM Evolution (EDGE); Project scheduling and open issues",</title>
        <tech>Tech. Rep, 3GPP TR 50.059</tech>
        <pages>version 4.0.0, 2001-04,</pages>
        <note>downloadable at</note>
        <web>http://www.etsi.org</web>
      </reference>
    </biblio>
  </content>
  <CitationContexts />
  <grants />
</document>

