<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <content>
    <headers headerID="p1x114.0y720.0">
      <title>Flexibility: Bringing the one constant factor into projects</title>
      <authors>
        <author>
          <author-first>Jan</author-first>
          <author-last>Jrging</author-last>
        </author>
      </authors>
      <institution>Industrieseminar, University of Mannheim</institution>
      <address>Schloss, D-68131 Mannheim</address>
      <phone>Tel.: +49 621 181-1750 Fax: +49 181-1579</phone>
      <email>E-Mail: juerging@is.bwl.uni-mannheim.de</email>
      <abstract>Abstract Despite the significant research carried out in project management a review by Morris and Hough (1987), a benchmark by Reichelt and Lyneis (1999), etc. reveal that most projects' performance cannot meet their expectations. System Dynamics has been applied intensively in project management models, and most successfully in `post mortem' analysises to identify the factors responsible for schedule and budget overruns. The paper intends to point out the flexibility's ability making a project system more stable and resistant to external influences. Extended Abstract The concept of flexibility enriching the traditional strategic success factors, which make up the magic triangle, has been coming up in the recent years. The flexibility's influence on the existing factors is not quite so clear yet. Does flexibility make it a square with four equally weighted factors, or is it rather a pyramid, where flexibility might influence cost, time, and quality with equal or different weight? In the area of manufacturing a lot of research regarding this topic already has been undertaken - in contrast to project management. It will be shown that project management still sticks to the traditional strategic success factors and that flexibility and project management so far have not been brought into a context. First, it is roughly presented what the findings in manufacturing are and analyzed whether the concept of flexibility can be transferred into project management. Flexibility in manufacturing In Manufacturing the relevance of the strategic success factors time, cost, and quality has changed over the time (Stalk, Hout, 1990). Between 1960 and 1970 firms tried to dominate markets by holding or gaining a dominant cost position. The quality area has followed these years and firms focused their efforts towards quality aspects of their product. Still the quality aspect is one of the most important strategic measurements, but a move towards a time-based competition has occurred and cycle times or product development times are more important than ever. Figure 1 shows the development of the emphasis given to the usual success factors. Figure 1: The changing role of success factors (Milling et al. 2000) Traditionally it was believed that one can not avoid trading off one capability for another. Empirical studies revealed that there are manufacturer who seem to have been able to defy that (Ferdows, De Meyer, 1990). A solution why this was possible might be flexibility. There are several examples where manufacturer could gain a competitive advantage through the one or the other version of flexibility (Upton, 1994). Indeed, the findings in manufacturing should be applicable to project management. The traditional performance measurements are here still the same. In project management the three performance measurements by now still are (i) being on schedule, (ii) below budget and (iii) delivering a product meeting the needed quality (Turner, 1999). But what is the answer to do well in all three categories? A definition of flexibility, one among others, given by Upton (1994), might help: "flexibility is the ability to change or react with little penalty time, effort, cost or performance" This implies that flexibility in the context of project management describes the capability to cope with changes in the project definition or scope and compensate them with little influences on schedule (time), costs and quality by appropriate management policies and actions. Following this definition flexibility is the factor that keeps projects on track regarding the success factors that make up the magic triangle. Literature review In contrast to traditional project management techniques the System Dynamics approach to project management takes a holistic view on the project and identifies the feedback structures within the project system. Realizing the dynamic nature of projects it seems obvious that System Dynamics can be used to understand and improve complex project systems. Lyneis (Lyneis, 2000) state that "In fact, without doubt project management applications have been the most extensive and successful use of system dynamics". A first model in this context was developed by Roberts (1964). Here the basic dynamics of R&amp;D projects were analyzed and the concept of perceived progress and real progress were introduced. This model was improved in order to manage concurrent projects. Probably the first time System Dynamics Model that has been successfully applied in project management was a shipbuilding claim against the US Navy (Cooper, 1980; Sterman, 2000) and it is important to note most of the major applications in practice refer to such dispute resolutions. The novelty in Cooper's work was the introduction of the rework cycle, a structure which copes with undiscovered rework, time to discover rework, work quality and varying working productivity. A summary of the basic feedback structures can be found in the model by Richardson and Pugh (1981). This R&amp;D project model focuses on the trade-off between hiring more staff and allowing</abstract>
      <keyword>quality time cost quality time cost quality time cost time</keyword>
    </headers>
    <body>a schedule slippage. These were only a few milestones and a lot more applications have been 
developed, for example by Abdel-Hamid and Madnick (1991), Homer et al. (1993), Ford and 
Sterman (1998), and Rodrigues and Williams (1998). A very good overview and a comparison 
with traditional management techniques are given by Rodrigues and Bowers (1996). 
The dynamic effects resulting from client changes and delays 
Typical project life-cycle diagrams shown in project-management textbooks, such as the 
`waterfall' model, assume that the client's role is confined to specifying the requirements, and the 
approving the final product. In practice the client frequently takes an essential part in the project, 
often by necessity, for example by approving sub-project milestones. The client can also require 
changes to the projects scope or the product definition. Such contract amendments can set up 
positive feed-back loops. Imagine for example a client demanding a high progress report. This 
will reduce the contractor's work productivity and cause the schedule to fall behind. This again 
will discomfort the client and end up in an even higher progress report demand. The single 
impact of a client change is straightforward to analyze, but when many client changes have to be 
considered the picture is a different. Quite often, effects combined together result in an even 
greater effect than the sum of their individual effects. This is sometimes called the portfolio effect 
(Eden, 2000). 
System Dynamics models have been used to identify and quantify the full impact of 
disturbances introduced by the client. In particular, this includes delays in approving in design 
documents and requirement changes after the project has been initiated. Rodrigues (1998) 
identifies the key `vicious circles', which are shown in Figure 2. 
Figure 2: Vicious circles in Projects (Rodrigues, 1998) 
Workscope 
changes/increases 
Delays in approving 
design documents 
Perceived 
Schedule 
Slippage 
Demand on 
progress reports 
Intolerance in 
delaying milestones 
Total extra effort 
perceived needed 
Schedule 
adjustments 
Schedule pressure 
Accept further 
changes 
Client trust in 
project team 
productivity 
Understanding about 
system functionality 
(trust in the 
requirements) 
Error generation 
Work out of 
sequence 
QA Effectivness 
(error detection) 
+ 
+ 
- 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
- 
- 
+ 
+ 
- 
- - 
- 

- Rework needed in 
testing 

stages+ 

+ The bold balancing loop in the middle represents, how normally changes with the client are 
negotiated, which is based on the negotiated perceived extra costs. Secondary effects are 
represented by the dashed lines, which are in the long run the reasons for over-runs. Having to do 
work out of the normal sequence is the first major effect, which can be brought about by client 
side delays in approving system design documents. Staff under schedule pressure tend to direct 
their efforts to system areas, which they believe are more stable. A direct increase in the number 
of errors made is going along with out of sequence work. As those errors are revealed in areas 
supposed to be stable the staff is loosing trust in the system's requirements. This will arouse a 
lower productivity. Poorer understanding of the system associated with schedule pressure causes 
the effectiveness of QA activities to deteriorate. A lower productivity and more flaws passing the 
QA will delay the schedule even more, which will lessen the client's tolerance accepting schedule 
adjustments and demand a higher progress reporting, which will keep the staff away from their 
real work. Often, the only way of getting the client to approve a schedule slippage is by allowing 
more changes for no extra costs. The square boxes in the diagram represent secondary ripple 
effects in which the clients play a major role. 
Flexibility in project management 
System Dynamics models have been used to identify and quantify the full impact of 
disturbances introduced by the client. Having already identified so many dynamics in project 
management - by a lot of `post mortem' applications - it might be very helpful to apply System 
Dynamics while the project is in progress. Resuming the given definition of flexibility it seems 
obvious that client side introduced disturbances (changes, delays, etc.) and flexibility can be used 
synonymously in the context of project management. It will be a great challenge to achieve 
comparable results as manufacturing did by exploring and implementing flexibility to their field. 
Project management has the potential to gain a lot by handling disturbances in a better way, 
because these are the challenges project managers are confronted with on a daily basis. But it is 
not a hopeless venture, because the findings for the `post mortem' analysis of projects are so far 
developed. Cooper (1997) assumes that the number of changes correlate to their impact by a 
nonlinear function, so that a hypothetical graph shown in Figure 3 might represent the reality. 
Figure 3: Correlation of the number of changes to their impact 
# of changes 
impact 
Normal 
behavior 
Behavior caused by 
increased flexibility 
The more flexible project will lower the impact's gradient in Figure 3 and shift the graph 
(dashed line) towards the abscissa. Following the above mentioned definition of flexibility the 
results of such a model should provide management policies to procure complex projects with a 
higher level of flexibility. Those policies will shift the graph towards the abscissa and projects 
will perform better regarding time, quality and cost. 
The outline of the paper is as follows. Firstly, a System Dynamics model is elaborated, which 
picks up the dynamics of client behavior impacting the project's performance. Preliminary results 
are retrieved from that model. Management policies that build up a flexible project will be 
examined. Examples are planning in appropriate time buffers for the changes, which will reduce 
the out of sequence work, or having, in a multi project organization, a stock of people working as 
firefighters. Another major issue when changes occur is the growing requirement of coordination 
(Ford, Sterman, 1998). By now it is not quite clear how to reduce these, and the presentation will 
concludes with more aspects of future research needed.</body>
    <biblio>
      <reference refID="p5x63.0y474.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Abdel-Hamid,</author-last>
            <author-first>T.</author-first>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>S.</author-first>
            <author-middle>E.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Madnick:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <booktitle>Software Project Dynamics: An Integrated Approach.</booktitle>
        <publisher>Prentice Hall:</publisher>
        <address>Englewood Cliffs NJ,</address>
        <date>1991.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p5x63.0y444.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Cooper,</author-last>
            <author-first>Kenneth</author-first>
            <author-middle>G.:</author-middle>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>System Dynamics methods in complex project management.</title>
        <booktitle>In: Managing and Modeling Complex Projects</booktitle>
        <editor>(Ed. T.M. Williams), NATO ASI Series, Dordrecht, the Netherlands,</editor>
        <publisher>Kluwer Academic Publisher,</publisher>
        <date>1997.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p5x63.0y401.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Cooper,</author-last>
            <author-first>Kenneth</author-first>
            <author-middle>G.:</author-middle>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>Naval Ship Production: A claim settled and a framework build,</title>
        <journal>in: Interfaces Vol.</journal>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <date>(6), 1980:</date>
        <pages>20-36.</pages>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p5x63.0y371.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Eden,</author-last>
            <author-first>C.,</author-first>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>T.</author-first>
            <author-last>Williams,</author-last>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>F.</author-first>
            <author-last>Ackermann,</author-last>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>S.</author-first>
            <author-last>Howick:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>The role of feedback dynamics in disruption and delay on the nature of disruption and delay (D&amp;D) in major projects, in:</title>
        <journal>Journal of the Operational Research Society,</journal>
        <volume>Vol. 51,</volume>
        <date>2000:</date>
        <pages>291-300.</pages>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p5x63.0y328.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Ford,</author-last>
            <author-first>David</author-first>
            <author-middle>N.,</author-middle>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>John</author-first>
            <author-middle>D.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Sterman:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>Dynamic modeling of product development processes, in:</title>
        <journal>System Dynamics Review,</journal>
        <volume>Vol. 14</volume>
        <number>(1),</number>
        <date>1998:</date>
        <pages>31-68.</pages>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p5x63.0y298.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Homer,</author-last>
            <author-first>J.,</author-first>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>J.</author-first>
            <author-middle>D.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Sterman,</author-last>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>B.</author-first>
            <author-last>Greenwood,</author-last>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>A.</author-first>
            <author-last>Perkola:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>Delivery time reduction in pulp and paper mill construction projects: a dynamic analysis of alternatives,</title>
        <conference>International System Dynamics Conference</conference>
        <date>1993.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p5x63.0y255.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Lyneis,</author-last>
            <author-first>James</author-first>
            <author-middle>M.,</author-middle>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>Kenneth</author-first>
            <author-middle>G.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Cooper,</author-last>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>Shannon</author-first>
            <author-middle>A.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Els:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>Strategic management of complex projects: a case study using system dynamics, in:</title>
        <journal>System Dynamics Review,</journal>
        <volume>Vol. 17</volume>
        <number>(3),</number>
        <date>2001:</date>
        <pages>237-260.</pages>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p5x63.0y211.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Milling,</author-last>
            <author-first>Peter</author-first>
            <author-middle>M.,</author-middle>
          </author>
          <author>
            <author-first>U.</author-first>
            <author-last>Schwellbach,</author-last>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>J.</author-first>
            <author-middle>H.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Thun:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>The Role of Speed in Manufacturing,</title>
        <editor>in: JosA. D. Machuca und Tomislav Mandakovic (Ed.):</editor>
        <title>POM Facing the New Millennium Evaluating the past, leading with the present and planning the future of Operations,</title>
        <conference>Sevilla</conference>
        <date>2000.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p5x63.0y153.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Morris,</author-last>
            <author-first>Peter</author-first>
            <author-middle>W.G.,</author-middle>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>George</author-first>
            <author-middle>H.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Hough:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <booktitle>The Anatomy of Major Projects, Chichester,</booktitle>
        <publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons,</publisher>
        <date>1987.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p5x63.0y123.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Reichelt,</author-last>
            <author-first>K.</author-first>
            <author-middle>S.,</author-middle>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>J.</author-first>
            <author-middle>M.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Lyneis:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>The dynamics of project performance: benchmarking the drivers of cost and schedule overrun, in:</title>
        <journal>European Management Journal,</journal>
        <volume>Vol. 17</volume>
        <date>(2), 1999.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p6x63.0y722.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Ridchardson,</author-last>
            <author-first>G.</author-first>
            <author-middle>P.,</author-middle>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>A.</author-first>
            <author-middle>L.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Pugh:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>Introduction to the System Dynamics Modeling with DYNAMO,</title>
        <address>Cambridge MA,</address>
        <publisher>MIT Press,</publisher>
        <date>1981.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p6x63.0y692.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Roberts,</author-last>
            <author-first>E.:</author-first>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <booktitle>The dynamics of Research and Development,</booktitle>
        <address>New York, Harper &amp; Row,</address>
        <date>1964.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p6x63.0y678.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Rodrigues,</author-last>
            <author-first>Alexander</author-first>
            <author-middle>G.,</author-middle>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>John</author-first>
            <author-last>Bowers:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>System Dynamics in project management: a comparative analysis with traditional methods, in:</title>
        <journal>System Dynamics Review,</journal>
        <volume>Vol. 12</volume>
        <number>(2),</number>
        <date>1996:</date>
        <pages>121-139.</pages>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p6x63.0y634.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Rodrigues,</author-last>
            <author-first>Alexander</author-first>
            <author-middle>G.,</author-middle>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>Terry</author-first>
            <author-middle>M.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Williams:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>System Dynamics in project management: assessing the impact of client behavior on project performance,</title>
        <conference>in: Journal of the Operational Research Society,</conference>
        <volume>Vol. 49</volume>
        <number>(1),</number>
        <date>1998:</date>
        <pages>2-15.</pages>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p6x63.0y590.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Stalk,</author-last>
            <author-first>G.,</author-first>
          </author>
          and
          <author>
            <author-first>T.</author-first>
            <author-middle>M.</author-middle>
            <author-last>Hout:</author-last>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>Competing Against Time -- How Time-based Competition is Reshaping Global Markets,</title>
        <publisher>The Free Press,</publisher>
        <address>New York,</address>
        <date>1991.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p6x63.0y561.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Sterman,</author-last>
            <author-first>John</author-first>
            <author-middle>D.:</author-middle>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>Business Dynamics: Systems Thinking and Modeling for a Complex World,</title>
        <address>Boston, McGraw-Hill,</address>
        <date>2000.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p6x63.0y532.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Turner,</author-last>
            <author-first>Rodney</author-first>
            <author-middle>J.:</author-middle>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <booktitle>The Handbook of Project-Based Management,</booktitle>
        <publisher>London, McGraw-Hill,</publisher>
        <date>1999.</date>
      </reference>
      <reference refID="p6x63.0y517.0">
        <authors>
          <author>
            <author-last>Upton,</author-last>
            <author-first>David</author-first>
            <author-middle>M.:</author-middle>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <title>The management of manufacturing flexibility, in:</title>
        <journal>California Management Review,</journal>
        <volume>Vol. 36</volume>
        <number>(2),</number>
        <date>1994:</date>
        <pages>72-90.</pages>
      </reference>
    </biblio>
  </content>
  <CitationContexts />
  <grants />
</document>

